Guide to the Max Rabinoff Papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Max Rabinoff Papers,
1908-1961
Rabinoff, Max.
ca. 974 items (4 boxes)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library, New York, NY.
4079244
Biographical Note
Musical impresario, international economist.
Scope and Content
Papers and correspondence of Rabinoff. Part of the collection relates to Rabinoff's endeavors in opera in Chicago, New York, and Boston and to his founding the American Institute of Operatic Art. The second part of the collection concerns his career as an economic advisor to the republics of Estonia, Georgia, and Azerbaijan, his work on the development of the Export Import Bank, and his interest in trade with Russia. Included in the collection are many photographs, clippings, and programs. Many of these pertain to the Russian ballerina Anna Pavlova who was introduced to American audiences by Rabinoff.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into 4 series:
Series I: Cataloged Correspondence
Series II: Arranged Correspondence
Series III: Artifacts/Ephemera
Series IV: Business
Subjects
American Institute of Operatic Art.; Export Import Bank.; Pavlova, Anna, 1881-1931.; Estonia--Economic conditions.; Georgia (Republic)--Economic conditions.; Azerbaijan--Economic conditions.; Soviet Union--Economic conditions.; Soviet Union--Commerce.; Ballerinas--Soviet Union.; Opera--Illinois--Chicago.; Opera--New York (State)--New York.; Opera--Massachusetts--Boston.; International economic relations.; International trade.; Photoprints.; Impresarios.; Economists.
Access Restrictions
This collection has no restrictions.
This collection is located on-site.
Acquisition
1967 M-67 Kraus, Mrs. Michael Gift
- Series I: Cataloged Correspondence
  The series contains the cataloged correspondence of Max Rabinoff, and is organized by last name of correspondent. Contracts, news articles, calling cards, and photographs of or about the correspondent are included. Correspondents include Lee de Forest, Otto Kahn, Leopold Stokowsky, and Vera Tchaikovsky.
  - Bernstein, Leonard To: Max Rabinoff, [n.p.], 2 October 1947, (t.l.s., 1p. ) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Coolidge, Calvin To: Mrs. John D. Sherman; Mrs. Thomas G. Winter, [n.p.], 7 Jan. 1924; 26 Dec. 1923; 18 Feb. 1925, ( t.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    [A series of letters reprinted as a presidential endorsment of The American Institute of Operatic Art ]
  - de Forest, Lee To: Max Rabinoff, Los Angeles, 28 October 1936, (2p. t.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - de Forest, Lee To: Max Rabinoff, [n.p.], 15 February 1938, (1p. t.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    [clipping is missing]
  - de Forest, Lee To: Max Rabinoff, [n.p.], 20 February 1939, (1p. t.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Diaghilev, Sergei Pavlovich & M.V. Gulok Drafts of contracts in Russian, St. Petersburg, Russia, 10 February 1911, ( a.d. and t.d) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Dreiser, Theodore To: Max Rabinoff, New York, 11 April 1929, (1p. a.l.s. photostat) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Eastman, George To: Max Rabinoff, Rochester, NY., 18 June 1923, (1p. t.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Ezekiel, Mordecai To: Max Rabinoff, [n.p.], 14 September 1933, (1p. t.l.s. photostat) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Farley, James A. To: John J. Hearne, New York, 10 September 1951, (1p. t.l.s. photostat) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Fisher, Irving To: C.P. Franchot, New Haven, Connecticut, 5 September 1933, (1p. t.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Mary Steele (secretary to Oscar Hammerstein 2nd.) To: Max Rabinoff, New York, 27 July 1951, (1p. t.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    [Included is a carbon of agreement for sale of the Philidelphia Opera House dated 26 April 1910]
  - Jones, Jesse Holman To: Max Rabinoff, Washington, D.C., 14 September 1933, (1p. t.l.s with photostat of original) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Jones, Jesse Holman To Max Rabinoff, Washington, D.C., 3 September 1935, (1p. t.l.s ) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    [Says photostat on the folio, but appears to be original]
  - Kahn, Otto Hermann To: Max Rabinoff, New York, Bar Harbor, Chicago, Waterford, London, Biarritz and others, 9 August 1910 - 4 January 1934, (30 t.l.s. or cables) (Box 1, Folder 2)
    [On various subjects ranging from the opera to U.S. Soviet trade]
  - Melba, Nellie To: Max Max Rabinoff, Burlingame, Ca., 2 April 1917, (1p. telegram) (Box 1, Folder 3)
    [Max Rabinoff telegram to Nellie Melba is missing]
  - Morris, Newbold To: V. Clement Jenkins, New York, 24 March 1943, (1p. t.l. (typescript copy of a signed note) (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Morros, Boris Mihailovitch To: Max Rabinoff, Hollywood, Ca., 28 October 1936, (1p. t.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 3)
    [ With NYT clipping on Morros]
  - Rabinoff, Max To: Herman Bernstein, New York, 27 May 1926, (1p. t.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Rabinoff, Max Memorandum on the late president Wilson, New York, [n.d.], (1p. m.s.) (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Rabinoff, Max contract with government of Mexico, Mexico City, 19 July 1910, (3p. t.d. carbon copy) (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Stokowski, Leopold To: Max Rabinoff, New York; Connecticut; Beverley Hills, 1941-1950, (10 t.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Strauss, Lewis L. To: Max Rabinoff, Washington, 29 March 1955, (1p. t.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Tchaikovsky, Vera To: [Max Rabinoff]; Max Rabinoff, [n.p.] [Paris] London, n.d., (3 a.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Tchaikovsky, Vera To: Max Rabinoff, Paris, November 1919, (2 calling cards; inscribed photo, 1p. a.n.s.) (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Tchaikovsky, Vera To: Max Rabinoff, Paris, 26 March 1921, (1p. marconigram) (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Tree, Sir Herbert Bearbohm Incomplete draft of contract with Max Rabinoff for an American tour, [n.p.], 1912 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Tynan, Brandon Contract to appear in the play The Mandarin signed by Herman Bernstein and Brandon Tynan with related letter and photograph, New York, 21 September 1920, (1p. t.l.s., 1p. contract) (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Series II: Arranged Correspondence
  The series contains correspondence arranged in alphabetical order by last name of correspondent. The series includes letters to Rabinoff from Lyn Stiebel-Hunt (professionally known as "Saharah") and New York Times music critic Howard Taubman.
  - A-Z, [v.p.], 1916-1960 (Box 1)
- Series III: Artifacts/Ephemera
  The series contains material related to Rabinoff's activities as a music impresario. It is arranged chronologically and consists of correspondence, musical programs, photographs, and clippings.
  - Contains information on Rabinoff's struggle to institute Sunday concerts in Chicago, on the Chicago auditorium, on performances for the Mexican government (1910), and on Rabinoff's wife, the soprano Marie La Salle, [n.p.], 1908-1916 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Contains information on Rabinoff's opera companies and protégés, [n.p.], 1917-1960 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Contains material from Rabinoff's scrapbook, some of which repeats the previous two files. Information is present on the performances for the Mexican government (1910), the production of The Miracle (1914), Marie La Salle, the US appearances of the Ukrainian National Chorus, the Imperial Balalaika Orchestra, and the American Institute of Operatic Arts at Stony Brook (1920s), [n.p.], 1910-1960 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Includes information on the Cosmopolitan Opera Company and Rabinoff's protégés, [n.p.], 1931-1961 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Chicago Grand Opera Company, [n.p.], 1908-1910 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Mexican National Opera, [n.p.], 1910-1944 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Boston Opera Company, [n.p.], 1910-1934 (Box 2, Folder 2 & 3)
  - Anna Pavlova (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - American Institute of Operatic Art (Box 2, Folder 5 & 6)
  - Cosmopolitan Opera Association, [n.p.], 1932-1943 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Photographs and biographical material (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Series IV: Business
  The series contains clippings, correspondence, speeches, and photostats relating to Rabinoff's work as economic adviser to Estonia and Georgia, and as a promoter of trade with Russia.
  - Documents and letters on Rabinoff's role as economic adviser to Estonia and Georgia, [n.p.], 1901-1950s (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Material relating to Rabinoff's efforts to promote trade with Russia, 1920-1950 (Box 3, Folder 2-4)